考虑这两个坐标框架，框架A和框架B.它们都是右撇子
Consider these two coordinate frames, frame A and frame B. They are both right-handed
坐标框架。
coordinate frames.
我们试图解决的问题是如何描述框架B的旋转
And the problem we’re trying to solve is how do we describe the rotation of frame B
关于框架A.想象一下，我们可以拿起框架A并在空间中旋转它
with respect to frame A. Imagine we could pick up frame A and rotate it in space so
它的轴与框架B的轴平行。我们怎么做？
that its axes were parallel to those of frame B. How do we do that?
好吧，一位非常着名的瑞士数学家LeonhardEuler提出了所谓的旋转
Well, a very famous Swiss mathematician, Leonhard Euler, came up with what’s called the Rotation
定理。
Theorem.
它指出两个三维坐标系由一系列基本相关
It states that two three-dimensional coordinate frames are related by a sequence of elementary
旋转，例如关于x轴，y轴，z轴的旋转。
rotations such as those about the x-axis, the y-axis, the z-axis.
我们需要应用不超过三个，但这个顺序的旋转需要
We need to apply no more than three of those, but the rotations in this sequence need to
关于不同的轴;那就是我们围绕x轴旋转，然后旋转y轴，然后旋转
be about different axes; that is we’d rotate about x-axis, then the y-axis, then maybe
x轴再次或可能绕z轴。
the x-axis again or maybe about the z-axis.
因此，任何旋转都可以表示为不超过三次旋转
So any rotation can be expressed in terms of no more than three rotations as long as
这三个旋转连续地围绕不同的轴。
those three rotations are consecutively about different axes.
让我们来演示这个旋转定理。
Let’s demonstrate this Rotation Theorem.
在这里，我有我的世界参考框架，在这里我有一个坐标框架
Here, I have my world reference frame and here I have a coordinate frame that has got
空间中的任意方向。
an arbitrary orientation in space.
因此，旋转定理说我应该能够采用这个坐标框架
And so, the Rotation Theorem says that I should be able to take this coordinate frame and
只需三次基本旋转即可实现这样的定位。
with simply three elementary rotations achieve an orientation like this.
所以，我将采用该世界参考框架的副本。
So, I’m going to take a copy of that world reference frame.
而且，我要做的第一件事是围绕x轴旋转一点。
And, first thing I’m going to do is to rotate it a little bit around the x-axis.
然后，我将围绕y轴旋转一点，然后我要去
Then, I’m going to rotate it a little bit around the y-axis, and then I’m going to
绕z轴旋转一下。
rotate it a bit around the z-axis.
如果我选择这个轴并把它放在这里，我们会看到它现在有一个大致的
And if I pick this axis up and put it in here, we’ll see that it now has a roughly the
与我开始使用的蓝框相同的方向。
same orientation as the blue frame that I started with.
所以，让我们写下所有可能的旋转序列，我们应用这个警告
So, let’s write down all the possible sequences of rotation, where we apply this caveat that
没有两个连续的旋转是围绕同一轴。
no two successive rotations are about the same axis.
事实上，有两个，我把它们写在这里。
In fact, there are two of them and I’ve written them all down here.
这些旋转分为两组，这里显示的组称为欧拉
These rotations fall into two groups and the group shown here are referred to as Euler
角。
angles.
并且，它们是围绕同一轴旋转两次的那些。
And, they are the ones where there are two rotations about the same axis.
第一个是绕X旋转，然后旋转Y，然后再旋转X.
The first one is rotation about X, then Y, then X again.
好吧，这一个是Y，然后是Z，然后是Y.
Well, this one over here is Y, then Z, then Y again.
因此，在欧拉角度组中，特定轴将出现两次，但不会连续出现两次。
So, in the Euler angle group, a particular axis will appear twice, but not twice consecutively.
这个特殊的群体;围绕Z旋转，然后围绕Y，然后围绕Z是相当的
This particular group; rotation around Z, then around Y, and then around Z is quite
通常称为欧拉角，但实际上有六个欧拉角。
commonly called Euler angles, but in fact there are six Euler angles.
因此，当我们谈论角度序列时，我们需要非常非常小心。
So, we need to be very, very careful when we talk about an angle sequence.
事实上，仅仅说欧拉角就不够好了。
It’s in fact not good enough just to say Euler angles.
我们应该非常具体并说出ZYZEuler角度。
We should be very specific and say ZYZ Euler angles.
不同的工程社区使用不同的约定，ZYZ惯例很漂亮
Different engineering communities use different conventions, and the ZYZ convention is pretty
常见于机器人和航空航天领域，但还有其他工程学科
common in robotics and in aerospace, but there are other engineering disciplines where they
使用不同的约定。
use different conventions.
当你谈到欧拉角时要非常非常小心。
Be very, very careful when you just talk about Euler angles.
让我们进行实验，在这里我们讨论的是ZYZ序列欧拉角。
Let’s experiment and here we’re talking about ZYZ sequence Euler angles.
我将使用工具箱函数eul2r，它采用三个角度参数，三个
I’m going to use the Toolbox function eul2r, which takes three angular arguments, the three
欧拉角。
Euler angles.
而且，我只是给它们简单的值：0.1,0。
And, I’m just going to give them simple values: 0.1, 0.
分别为2和0.3弧度。
2 and 0.3 radians respectively.
并且，这是产生的旋转矩阵，其对应于三个欧拉角。
And, here is the resulting rotation matrix that corresponds to the three Euler angles.
因此，您可以将此视为坐标方向的两种替代表示
So you can think of this as two alternative representations for orientation of the coordinate
帧。
frame.
我们可以将它表示为3乘3正交矩阵，或者我们可以用三个数字表示它
We can represent it as a 3 by 3 orthogonal matrix or we can represent it by three numbers
这是欧拉角。
which are the Euler angles.
我可以执行逆操作。
I can perform the inverse operation.
我可以将旋转矩阵转换为欧拉角。
I can convert a rotation matrix to Euler angles.
为此，我使用函数tr2eul，然后传入我们的旋转矩阵
To do that, I use the function tr2eul and I pass in the rotation matrix which we’ve
刚刚计算出来
just computed.
在这里我们有欧拉角。
And here we have the Euler angles.
所以我可以将欧拉角转换为旋转矩阵，将旋转矩阵转换回欧拉角。
So I can convert Euler angles to a rotation matrix, a rotation matrix back to Euler angles.
让我们来看一个稍微不同的情况，其中中欧拉角是负的
Let’s have a look at a slightly different case where the middle Euler angle is a negative
数字和结果是旋转矩阵。
number and the result is rotation matrix.
它与我们以前的旋转矩阵不同，因为它是不同的
It’s a different rotation matrix to the one we had before because it’s a different
欧拉角集。
set of Euler angles.
现在我将这个旋转矩阵转换回欧拉角。
Now I’ll convert this rotation matrix back to Euler angles.
我们将看到我们最终得到的欧拉角不是欧拉角
And we’ll see that the Euler angles that we end up with are not the Euler angles that
我们一开始。
we started with.
因此，当我们考虑表示方向时，这是另一个重要的考虑因素
So this is another important consideration when we look at representing orientation in
这三个角度序列的术语：它们不是唯一的，但它们是两个不同的
terms of these three-angle sequences: that they are not unique, but they are two different
欧拉角的集合导致完全相同的旋转矩阵。
sets of Euler angles which result in exactly the same rotation matrix.
只是为了验证是这种情况，我将转换这个不同的集合
And just to verify that that is the case, I’m going to convert this different set
欧拉角与旋转矩阵的关系。
of Euler angles to a rotation matrix.
我将通过该答案，我们可以看到生成的旋转矩阵。
I’m going to pass that answer in and we can see the resulting rotation matrix.
我们可以看到它与这里的完全相同。
And we can see that it is exactly the same as this one here.
所以有两组欧拉角，它们的方向完全相同
So there are two sets of Euler angles which result in exactly the same orientation in
空间，相同的旋转矩阵。
space, the same rotation matrix.
另一组旋转序列通常称为万向角。
The other group of rotation sequences are commonly called Cardan angles.
这些都是以一位着名的，或臭名昭着的意大利人的名字命名的，他是一名医生，一名占星师
These are named after a very famous, or infamous, Italian character who was a doctor, an astrologer
和一个赌徒，并在监狱中度过了一段异端邪说。
and a gambler and spent some time in jail for heresy.
但他是一个非常非常有创造力的人，他发明了组合锁并发明了通用
But a very, very inventive person, he invented the combination lock and he invented the universal
关节，将扭矩从汽车前部的发动机传递到车轮
joint, the thing that transmits torque from an engine in the front of the car to the wheels
在车的后面。
at the back of the car.
他还广泛发表概率论，是最早解决立方数的人之一
He also published widely on probability and was one of the first people to solve cubic
和四次多项式方程。
and quartic polynomial equations.
所以一个非常非常聪明的人。
So a very, very bright person.
万向角涉及围绕不同轴的旋转。
The Cardan angles involve rotations around different axes.
所以在旋转序列中没有重复的字母。
So no letter is repeated in the rotation sequence.
它们中的两个通常被称为滚动角，俯仰角和偏航角。
The two of them are often referred to as roll, pitch and yaw angles.
这是序列XYZ或序列ZYX。
That’s the sequence XYZ or the sequence ZYX.
哪个特定的用作滚动，俯仰，偏航角度取决于上下文
And which particular one is used as roll, pitch, yaw angles depends a bit on the context
这个问题。
of the problem.
滚动，俯仰，偏航角度是三维物体定向的常见惯例
Roll, pitch, yaw angles are a really common convention for orientation of bodies in three-dimensional
空间。
space.
我们使x轴指向前方，因此滚动角度围绕x轴旋转。
We have the x-axis pointing forward and so the roll angle is rotation around the x-axis.
这是我们做的第一次轮换。
So that’s the first rotation that we do.
现在我们围绕y轴执行旋转，这称为俯仰。
Now we perform a rotation around the y-axis and that’s referred to as pitch.
这就是这种动作。
So that’s this sort of motion.
然后在旋转之后，我们围绕z轴进行旋转，我们将其称为
And then after that rotation, we do a rotation around the z-axis and we refer to that as
偏航运动。
yaw motion.
因此，滚动，俯仰，偏航对姿态的描述是围绕x轴旋转，然后是围绕
So roll, pitch, yaw description of attitude is a rotation around the x-axis, then around
y轴，然后绕z轴。
the y-axis, and then around the z-axis.
证明这种连续三次旋转原理的方法是用这种机制，
A way to demonstrate this principle of three consecutive rotations is with this mechanism,
一种称为万向节机制的东西。
a thing called a Gimbal mechanism.
所以，这里有两个坐标框架。
So, there are two coordinate frames here.
我们这里有世界参考坐标系，大红框。
We have the world reference coordinate frame here, the big red frame.
而且，我们这里的中间有一个较小的坐标系。
And, we have a smaller coordinate frame in the middle here.
现在，我们可以围绕x轴旋转，这是一个这样的运动。
Now, we can make a rotation around the x-axis, which is a motion like this.
我们可以围绕y轴旋转，这是一个像这样的旋转。
We can rotate around the y-axis, which is a rotation like this.
而且，我们可以围绕z轴旋转。
And, we can rotate around the z-axis.
所以，我可以将这个内部坐标框架放在我喜欢的任何方向和万向节上
So, I can put this inner coordinate frame at any orientation that I like and the gimbals
会找到合适的角度来实现这一点。
will find the appropriate angles to allow that to happen.
因此，这非常清楚地表明可以实现该内框架的任何方向
So this demonstrates very clearly shows that any orientation of this inner frame can be achieved
通过围绕x，y和z轴任意选择三个旋转角度。
by arbitrary choice of three rotation angles around the x, y, and z-axis.
让我们来看看实际中的一些滚动，俯仰，偏航角度。
Let’s have a look at some roll, pitch, yaw angles in practice.
这是美国宇航局从60年代末到70年代初期的月球模块的示意图。
This is a schematic diagram of NASA’s lunar module from the late ’60s and early ’70s.
我们可以看到这里指出的坐标框架。
We can see the coordinate frames indicated on here.
我们可以看到它们将滚动定义为围绕z轴的旋转，该旋转朝向前方
We can see that they define roll as rotation around the z-axis which is toward the front
对于车辆而言，它们将偏航定义为围绕x轴（垂直方向）
of the vehicle and they have defined yaw as being around the x-axis which is the vertical
该特定车辆的轴。
axis for this particular vehicle.
滚动，俯仰，偏航角度的MATLAB函数与Euler非常相似
The MATLAB functions for roll, pitch, yaw angles are very similar to those for Euler
角。
angles.
我们使用函数rpy2r，我们传递滚动，俯仰，偏航角度。
We used the function rpy2r and we pass in the roll, pitch, yaw angles.
我刚刚在这里编写了一些简单的数字。
I’ve just made up some simple numbers here.
滚动角为0.1
The roll angle is 0.1
弧度。
radians.
俯仰角为0.2弧度。
The pitch angle is 0.2 radians.
偏航角为0.3弧度。
And the yaw angle is 0.3 radians.
这是产生的正交旋转矩阵。
And this is the resulting orthogonal rotation matrix.
再一次，有一个反函数。
Once again, there is an inverse function.
所以tr2rpy，我传递旋转矩阵，结果是滚动，俯仰，偏航角度，
So tr2rpy, and I pass in the rotation matrix and the result are roll, pitch, yaw angles,
和我开始时的那些一样。
the same as those that I started with.